Getting into the air is not easy.
For many birds it is by far the most exhausting
bit of the whole business of flight.
But these shearwaters here in Japan
have adopted a very labour-saving way...
Whoops! There we go,
a labour-saving way of doing so.
They've taken to climbing trees.
This particular tree is by far
the most suitable for the take-off,
and that bird may have come
from as far as 30 or 40 yards away,
wandering across the forest floor
in order to climb it and get to the launch pad.
There's another.
40 feet up, a bend in the trunk
makes a perfect platform for a take-off.
These shearwaters
will spend most of their lives in the air.
They are true seabirds.
They only come to land in order to nest.
This particular species is
exceptional in nesting in woodland,
most of them nest right on the edge of cliffs
and all of them get into the air
by the simple method of simply falling into space.
The land birds, on the other hand,
have much greater problems.
Most of them have to be able to get into the air
from the ground with a standing start.
And that takes a lot more energy.
A pigeon begins by jumping vertically upwards.
As it leaves the ground,
it opens its wings and sweeps them forward,
fanning the air downwards with maximum force.
The second stroke must be equally vigorous,
pushing the bird upwards.
If now it leans forward
and starts to go ahead.
But the effort involved has been huge.
Birds only a little bigger than a pigeon
can't do this twice in quick succession.
And a bird as big as an albatross
can't do it at all.
It has to use yet another way
of getting into the air.
It taxies, along a runway.
It's a method we use too, in our machines.
For the majority of birds
the most exhausting part of flight is now over.
Those shearwaters achieved it by climbing trees,
the pigeon jumped and flapped,
and aeroplanes and albatross did it by running
and creating a flow of air over their wings.
When they do actually get into the air,
a bird's flight seems almost effortless.
And when you watch
a really superb flyer like these albatross,
then they seem to be defying the law of nature.
They are, after all, big heavy birds.
How is it that they
can withstand the pull of gravity
that keeps the rest of us
tied so firmly to the ground?
The secret is a wing
with a thick, rounded front edge
that curves gently downwards
towards the back edge, which is very thin.
As thin, in fact, as a feather.
As the bird glides forward,
the air flowing under the wing is impeded
by the wing's downward curve.
So it becomes slightly compressed
and that pushes the wing up.
At the same time,
the air flowing across the top of the wing
is deflected upwards by the wing's front edge
so reducing its pressure.
If the air is moving fast enough,
then the slight suction from above
combined with the push from beneath
will be enough to lift the bird into the air,
as it did during take-off,
and ample to keep it aloft, as it's doing now.
The trick is to make sure that the air
does flow over the wing sufficiently quickly.
Upward air currents
can also sustain a bird in flight
and that is just what are created when
breezes, blowing in from the sea, hit a cliff.
If they are really strong,
such up-draughts can be so powerful
that they alone will keep an albatross in the air.
0ut at sea, the waves deflect the wind upwards
in somewhat smaller gusts
and the albatross is so skilful
that it can sail on them for hours
with scarcely a movement of its wings.
Most birds, however, once in flight,
have to create that air-flow across their wings
by another method.
They drive themselves forward by flapping.
This knot is 'rowing' through the air, stretching
its wings forwards, and beating them downwards.
0n the upstroke it half-folds them,
to reduce their surface area
and therefore their resistance to the air.
The feathers on its wing
slide smoothly over one another
so that although
the wing is continuously changing shape,
its surface remains
perfectly smooth and streamlined.
Its body is also streamlined
by its coat of feathers,
and its feet are pressed against its tail
so that drag is kept to a minimum.
This mallard is flying at nearly 40 miles an hour,
but its streamlining is so perfect
that there is scarcely a ruffle to its feathers.
It's only from behind that you notice
the little flicks of the feathers over its tail
and the back edge of its wings
which show just how fast it's travelling.
To see just how important streamlining is,
and how much energy it can save,
just watch this osprey as it goes fishing.
To take off again, with the fish in its talons,
the bird has to beat its wings
with all the strength it can muster.
But even now it is in the air,
the fish hanging broadside.
It creates so much drag that the osprey has
great difficulty in making any headway at all.
But it knows how to solve the problem.
Gripping the fish with just one foot,
it manages to bring its other foot forward.
Now, using both feet, the bird changes
the position of the fish so that it faces ahead
and its streamlined shape
reduces its drag so much
that the osprey's wing-beats
become almost leisurely.
Flying in formation also saves energy.
A big bird like a pelican
creates a trail of turbulence in the air
and this can give a following bird lift.
The effect is at its greatest
directly behind a bird's wing-tip,
so that is the best place for a following bird to fly.
Pelicans also save some 20% of
their energy by mixing flapping with gliding.
Aerodynamically it's more profitable for a bird
to time its flaps with those of the bird ahead.
So it is the pelicans who give breathtaking
displays of synchronised formation flying.
The most economical way of flying, however,
is to draw almost all the energy you need
directly from the sun.
As it warms the ground in the morning,
the rocks reflect its heat
and shimmering columns of air,
thermals, begin to rise.
Griffin vultures in Spain now leave the ledges
on the cliffs where they have spent the night
and launch themselves into the air.
With the thermals rising powerfully
beneath their outstretched wings
they sail effortlessly upwards.
All they have to do is to make sure
that they remain within the column of warm air.
So dozens of them spiral together in tight circles,
adjusting their flight with
the tiniest movements of their wings and tails.
There can be no more economical flight than this.
The vulture's ability to 'read' the air conditions
above their landscape,
and detect exactly where the thermals are
at their most powerful, seems almost uncanny.
But in recent years,
human beings have also mastered it.
When you hit a thermal in a glider,
you really feel it.
Your stomach drops beneath your feet.
- 0ohh!
- I'm going to roll into the thermal here.
Glider pilots spend a lot of time
going around in circles just as birds of prey do,
because a thermal's a rising column of air
and in order to stay in it you have to turn.
There's nothing to see though, is there?
Apart from what's on the ground.
You can't see anything in the air
to indicate a thermal
Right now there's no
cumulus cloud over this thermal
But often there is. If you look over there,
you can see all those cumulus clouds.
Underneath most of those
there would be a thermal,
and that's one of those indicators of lift,
that's one thing we look for,
and that's what birds look for also
when they fly, I'm sure.
Feel that! Now there's
a big rocky outcropping. Just look at that.
Now you can see the altimeter winding up.
Look at that.
- How high could we go with this?
- Probably up to 14-15,000 feet with no
problem.
- And do the birds go as high as that?
- I've seen birds up to 16-18,000 feet.
- They are just out there flying for fun.
- How do you know that?
Because how can you see
a mouse from 18,000 feet? Not hardly.
And they do all kinds of tricks and aerobatics.
Look at this. We're really going up now.
The pressure on the wings
is actually bending them, isn't it?
The spar is slightly flexible,
so when you develop more lift,
the spar actually bends upwards a little bit.
Very similar to a bird.
Every flight has to end in a landing.
That requires less energy,
but perhaps more skill if disaster is to be avoided,
particularly if you are a big bird like a pelican.
A swan, one of the heaviest of flying birds,
can only come down on the smoothest
and most forgiving of natural surfaces; water.
There you can use your feet as brakes.
Albatross are not so lucky.
They have to alight on the ground.
Indeed their landings seem scarcely better
than controlled accidents.
Most birds, however, have to come down
with much greater precision than that.
They may have to land, after all,
on a narrow ledge or a very thin branch.
To do that they have to lower their flaps,
put down the undercarriage
and put on their brakes so that they
lose all air speed at the precise moment
that they come alongside their perch.
That requires great judgement and co-ordination.
A Griffin vulture is
able to exploit the position of its nest,
which is nearly always on the ledge of a cliff.
It descends towards it at speed.
It aims for a point below its nest
and then brakes by swooping upwards
so that as it arrives at its ledge
its forward speed is zero.
Landing into the wind helps any bird
by keeping air flowing over the wings
and maintaining lift until the last moment.
So, one way or another, birds manage to
complete an operation fraught with danger,
with virtually total success.
As anyone who has had to pay for
excess baggage at an airport knows,
if you travel by air, it is important
to keep your weight down.
This magnificent golden eagle manages
to do that in a most thoroughgoing way.
It's about the same size, I suppose, as a bulldog.
But I couldn't hold a bulldog on my wrist.
But this bird
only weights about a quarter as much.
So how do birds manage to keep so light?
A beak is not so weighty as the bony jaws
and teeth of a mammal like a bulldog
or one of the birds' reptilian ancestors.
Its disadvantage is that a bird can't chew.
It can pluck, crush or, like an eagle, tear and rip.
They also have weight-saving features
inside their bodies,
a skeleton with fewer bones
than a mammal's, no tail-bone,
one wing-bone instead of five fingers,
and a slim pelvis fused to the backbone.
And the bones themselves are not solid
like a mammal's, but hollow.
Inside they have a lattice of cross-struts
so they are nonetheless very strong.
But the most remarkable
weight-saving features of all
are those things that only birds possess:
their feathers.
They look simple, but in fact
they have a very complex structure.
The quills are hollow and very light,
yet resilient and extremely strong.
The filaments on either side of the quills
are fringed with microscopic hooks
that link them to their neighbours so that they
all latch together to form a continuous surface.
And that means that if a feather
gets damaged or over-strained,
it can be repaired instantly. It can be zipped up.
Not surprisingly, all birds lavish
a great deal of attention on their feathers.
After all, their lives depend on them.
And since birds have no hands,
they have little alternative
but to care for them with their beaks.
But one bird, uniquely, can't do that.
The sword-billed hummingbird
has a beak that is so long
that there is no way
that its tip can touch its feathers.
It has to comb its plumage with one foot
while balancing on its perch with the other.
Not easy!
A good bath is also important in keeping
the feathers clean and in first-class condition.
Most birds take one every day
and, watching them doing so,
it's difficult to avoid coming to the conclusion
that they enjoy it just as much as we do.
Not all birds, of course, can get to water
that is deep enough for bathing.
Then, like the quail that lives on dry plains
and during the summer seldom finds
so much as a puddle, they may have to use dust.
This may not exactly make them cleaner, but
it does, apparently, help in dislodging parasites
such as lice that nibble their feathers,
mites that scavenge bits of dead skin
and ticks that suck their blood.
Many parrots and cockatoos grow special feathers
that fray at the end into a fine powder.
These feathers are
scattered throughout the plumage,
and as a bird such as a cockatoo
scratches itself at the end of its toilet,
the powder is dislodged in clouds
and is caught in its ruffled feathers.
Exactly how this powder
improves the feathers is not really certain,
but it is probable that it helps with waterproofing
as well as by discouraging parasites.
Parasites, in fact, are such a problem
that some birds are thought to
recruit assistants to help in getting rid of them.
Ants!
Crows and jays deliberately land on an ant's nest
and stir up the colony so that the angry insects
come rushing out and swarm all over them.
In their irritation the ants discharge formic acid
which is a particularly powerful insecticide.
But we don't really understand this behaviour.
It may be that the birds are stimulating the ants
to get rid of their formic acid
so that they are more digestible as meals.
Regular, meticulous maintenance is essential
for maximum efficiency and safety in the air,
and that applies to everything that flies.
Well, that was about 500 miles an hour
and of course birds can't equal that.
But nonetheless, before aeroplanes were invented,
a bird was the fastest living thing in the air.
The peregrine holds the record.
Diving on its prey
it can exceed 200 miles an hour.
It achieves maximum aerodynamic efficiency
by sweeping back its wings, like the jet fighter.
Then it accelerates by beating them.
The barn owl, on the other hand,
owes its success as a hunter
to its ability to fly extremely slowly.
It hunts voles and mice
and, to find them in the grass
it has to search very intently, and that takes time.
Its wings therefore
are shaped very differently from a peregrine's.
They are rounded in outline and much broader
which gives the maximum lift at slow speeds.
But the barn owl also has
a very special adaptation for this kind of hunting.
The rodents it seeks are often invisible
from the air, hidden beneath the matted grass.
The barn owl detects them
by the rustling sounds they make.
To do that, it has extremely acute hearing,
the sounds being focused by the hair-like
feathers of the discs on either side of its head.
But if it is to hear them
it has to fly very quietly indeed,
and its wings are fitted with silencers.
Fluffy margins to its wing feathers.
So, in the evenings, a barn owl can
waft over the countryside as silent as a moth.
This little dot, suspended in the sky,
might seem to be the slowest flyer of all.
It's a kestrel It's not, in fact, truly stationary.
It's facing into a gentle wind,
so there is a current of air passing over its wings.
And that gives it all the lift it requires.
Silence is not as important for the kestrel
as it is for the barn owl, for it hunts by sight.
The wind has dropped a little.
Now, to keep its position relative to the ground
it has to flap
to keep the air moving over its wings.
It's spotted something,
a quick turn into the wind, and a drop;
a turn back to face
the wind for a stationary check;
another quick look;
but whatever it was, has gone.
0nly one group of birds
can manage to hover for any length of time
without the help of a head-wind:
the hummingbirds.
Their wings work in a way
quite unlike that used by any other birds.
They beat routinely 25 times a second,
so fast that they make the humming noise
that gives them their name.
It is impossible to see how they operate
unless the camera slows them down.
The wings have become, in effect,
twirling blades that create down-draughts,
rather like those that man produces
with his hovering machines.
Helicopters, however, have a very special device,
a wheel revolving continuously on an axle.
No bird or any other animal has yet evolved
a mechanism that can exactly parallel this.
But hummingbirds have the next best thing:
wings which beat in a figure of eight
and flick over on the backstroke.
Unlike the wings of other birds,
they are symmetrical in cross-section
and work equally well
with either surface uppermost.
By changing the angle of the beat,
the thrust can be directed not only downwards,
but either forwards or backwards.
So a hummingbird, steering with its tail,
can move through the air in any direction.
Beating wings at such speed, however,
uses a lot of fuel
Even at rest, hummers need a great deal
just to keep their bodies ticking over.
So they have to refuel very frequently.
But their fuel stations, flowers, close at night.
What do they do then?
This is a particular problem in the Andes,
where the nights can be very cold indeed.
As evening comes on, the hillstar hummingbird
makes its way to
its regular roosting place, in a cave.
After its regular toilet,
it settles down for the night,
and in effect turns off all its motors.
Its heart, that in flight
contracted a thousand times a minute,
slows until its beat is virtually undetectable.
Its body temperature falls dramatically
and its breathing seems to cease altogether.
It is doing what a hedgehog does in winter,
it is hibernating.
But for a hummingbird,
winter comes 365 times a year.
The sun returns,
and the temperature begins to rise.
The hillstar starts up its motors.
Its heart beat accelerates,
its muscles slowly warm to flying temperature.
A quick pre-flight check.
And it's off again.
At higher altitudes,
it seldom gets really warm even at midday.
This is the territory of the giant hummingbird.
It's as big as a thrush.
Great size helps in retaining body heat,
but this is as big as a hummingbird can get.
Any larger and it couldn't beat its wings
fast enough for this kind of flight.
And this is one of the smallest of all birds,
the purple-collared woodstar from Ecuador
with a wingspan of scarcely more than two inches.
Small wings are easier to flap,
but the smaller they are, the faster they have
to move to produce sufficient downwards thrust,
and this hummingbird can beat its wings
at an astonishing 75 times a second.
It is barely bigger than a moth.
Indeed this moth looks so like a tiny hummingbird
that some people in the south of England,
where it appears regularly in the summer,
think that they have been visited
by a real hummer.
The ability to fly
gave birds the freedom of the planet.
Rivers, deserts, seas, even mountain ranges
are no obstacle to them as they are
to land-bound creatures such as ourselves.
They can fly relatively easily and quickly
to collect a sudden glut of food.
And that is exactly what has happened here.
I'm in northern Canada.
It's June,
the beginning of the short Arctic summer.
The rising temperatures have caused
the plants to put out new leaves and roots,
and tens of thousands of snow geese
have come here to graze.
They nested almost as soon as they arrived
and many have already got families.
Even hummingbirds have come up to the far north
to collect nectar from the bushes that are now
briefly blooming within sight of glaciers.
0n the Arctic coasts,
little waders, western sandpipers,
are collecting a rich harvest of small worms
that are swarming in the mud.
In the middle of the continent, on the prairies,
sorghum and other grain crops are
ripening in the summer sun.
Dickcissels, relatives of the common sparrow,
have come up here to take their percentage.
The warm weather
has caused swarms of insects to hatch
and they provide the dickcissels
with the protein that is essential
for the nourishment
of their swiftly growing young.
Hawks are also breeding here in the north.
They were attracted by the seasonal abundance
of voles and other small mammals,
as well as the finches and songbirds
that they need to feed their young.
But the superabundance of summer is brief.
By the end of July
the days are noticeably shortening.
Many of the trees
are preparing to shed their leaves.
The birds that flew up for the summer banquet
can no longer stay.
All across the northern hemisphere
the story is the same.
From eastern Siberia across Asia and Europe,
to the woodlands and tundra of north America,
birds are starting to fly south.
The sandpipers are stocking up for
the 6,000 mile journey that lies ahead of them.
They eat so voraciously
that they will nearly double their weight,
putting on layers of fat
on their upper thighs and their flanks.
They even shrink their internal organs,
partially absorbing them
as though they were food reserves
and replacing them
with more readily available fat.
They must wait for the right weather conditions,
and then, when the wind
blows strongly from the north, they set off.
Hawks and vultures are also now
finding it harder to discover any food.
They too must prepare to leave.
But the weather they require for their journeys
is rather different.
They need a good hot day when the thermals
are shimmering upwards from the rocks
that are still warming in the late summer sun.
As the last thermals of summer start to rise,
the birds circle up to great heights,
10,000 feet or more, to give themselves
a good start for the long journey ahead.
As they glide southwards, slowly losing height,
they will look for another thermal
and make for its base so that once again
they will be lifted high enough to reach the next.
The snow geese are already on their way,
their departure triggered by the shortening days
and the dropping temperatures.
They will rely on straightforward muscle power.
They will travel continuously for great lengths
of time, both through the day and the night.
The raptors, however,
have had to stop to overnight in a roost.
Without thermals they can't travel far.
But the snow geese fly on.
The exertion of continuously beating their wings
creates a lot of heat in their bodies,
so travelling in the cool of the night
does, in fact, suit them.
They navigate by the stars.
If the skies are heavily overcast for long periods
they may lose their way, but that is exceptional
Day returns and the stars fade.
Now they steer by the sun.
But the sun, of course,
moves from east to west during the day,
so the fact that they are able
to use it for navigation
means that they must have internal clocks
and know fairly exactly what the time is.
Members of the same family travel together,
calling to one another as they go.
And the geese have made it.
One of them has been recorded as covering
an astonishing 1,700 miles in a mere 70 hours.
These fields in California will be their home
until they return north on their spring migration.
The sandpipers have gone even further.
They have now reached Mexico.
But they will spend only a few days here
for this is merely a refuelling stop.
They feed intensively, replacing
the fat reserves that they have lost.
The raptors, so conscious of
the nature of the land beneath them
that generates thermals on which they depend,
also look to it for their signposts.
They are now passing Mexico's highest mountain,
the Pico de 0rizaba.
There are no thermals to be found over the sea,
so they are tied to the land,
and that means they have to go all the way round
the western side of the Gulf of Mexico.
There is, of course, a short cut,
directly south across the sea.
Astonishingly, the little ruby-throat hummingbird
tackles that 500 mile long journey.
It must necessarily be non-stop
for a hummingbird cannot land on the water.
A feeder in Texas provides a ruby-throat
with a final top-up of nectar.
Its cruising speed is about 27 miles an hour.
So, if conditions are good, it could make
the crossing by flying for a little over 18 hours.
But that is right on the very limit of its endurance.
If even a light head-wind
springs up it will perish at sea.
Delphiniums blooming on the Mexican shore
await with life-saving nectar.
A ruby-throat arrives after its epic journey
and feeds urgently before it runs out of fuel,
and it's fatally grounded.
But even now its journey is not finished.
It still has several hundred miles to go
and may travel as far as the Panama border.
The hawks and vultures,
travelling round the western side of the Gulf,
have now reached Panama City.
They came from all over North America,
converged on the Isthmus
and travelled together
down that narrow corridor of land
so that now, for the only time each year,
they form dense flocks.
Below, on the mud of Panama Bay,
the sandpipers are feeding.
This, at last, is the end of their journey.
The mud here will never freeze,
the sea will enrich it daily,
and each bird returns every year
to exactly the same patch.
The raptors rise
once more in an immense vortex.
From here they will take
their separate ways all over South America,
some going as far south as Argentina.
0nly by dispersing widely
will each bird find enough prey to sustain itself.
The dickcissels have also travelled
down the Isthmus of Panama.
They too have come from all over North America
and have been funnelled together
into flocks of gigantic size and density.
This surely is the very acme of flying skill.
How they co-ordinate their flight
in these extraordinary concentrations,
changing direction within it, as if with one mind,
is one of the unsolved mysteries of ornithology.
Years ago, they, like the hawks and eagles,
would have travelled on south from here
and spread over
the plains of northern South America
to feed on the seeds of wild grasses.
But here in Venezuela,
they find great fields of cultivated grain,
exactly like they found up in the north.
So they have no need to disperse,
but remain together
and devastate the crops wherever they settle.
It seems they positively
prefer one another's company.
Some of the flocks may be half a million strong.
And man's practice of intensive cultivation
allows them to stay and feed together.
At night they select a relatively small patch
within a huge field of sugar cane
where the whole half million roost,
half a dozen birds to a single stem.
Flying, when all is said and done,
takes a great deal of energy.
So birds have huge appetites
and have to spend much of their lives
in an unending search for food
to fuel their expensive lifestyle.
Just how they find it, we will be looking at
in the next programme in The Life of Birds.